Eric Bolstad

425.246.8083 (m) | ebol2000@gmail.com LinkedIn: <u>www.linkedin.com/in/ebolstad</u>

Professional Summary

Software development professional with 16 years of experience with Microsoft stack including C#, WPF, WCF. Well versed in all aspects of the SDLC. 7 years experience implementing and growing cloud infrastructure for popular Saas CRM (customer relationship management) solution. Experienced developer who can help by building sustainable software for the long term, mentor junior developers, and help build your team to it's potential. My passion is building simplified and encapsulated software with low coupling, high readability, and therefore high re-usability.

Key Characteristics

- Software developer at heart (and still developing)... full stack .Net developer
- Proven leader and project manager who drives SOLID development principles from the gathering of requirements through deployment and maintenance of the product
- Strong team building and processes leading to successful and efficient software project completion
- Experience with complex, hybrid systems leveraging cloud webservices, web, mobile and Windows development
- Balanced approaches to complicated trade-offs of schedule, scope, and quality of products

Technology

Languages/Platforms: C# (.net 1.0 through 4.5), TSQL, WPF, WCF, ASP.Net, Java Script, JQuery, XML, HTML, C, C++, VB.Net, Telerik Winform Controls

Webservices: .Net Web API, ASMX, JSON REST

Database: MS SQL 7 to MS SQL 2014, sprocs, views, triggers, performance and optimization, deadlock troubleshooting and resolution, etc

Cloud: Designed and implemented bulk of our Windows based cloud infrastructure. Replaced partial infrastructure with AWS (Amazon Web Services). Assisted marketing with replacing our company website completely on AWS.

Experience

Avidian Technologies Bellevue, WA 6/2012 - Present

Director of Software Development

Promoted to take over former CTO's responsibilities when he left the company. We are still a small team, so I continue to share duties as a part-time developer though I probably get less than 30% of my time left for development. While I continue to serve as a technical resource, I now spend a lot of my time managing our scrum process, helping mentor team members, and defining requirements for stake holders. Much of my former responsibilities still exist with several added ones including:

- **Product Management**: Gathering/writing requirements, holding reviews, formulating road-maps for the coming year.
- People Management: Have build 100% of current team with no turnover for the
 past three years. Team has jelled and works together very effectively with mutual
 respect. Also manage or delegate managing our Agile Scrum process.
- **Cloud Management:** Our team is 100% responsible for managing our cloud servers health and well being. We are responsible for maintaining thousands of databases.
- Manage T3 Support Escalations
- **Hiring:** Have hired all of current dev team. We use a multi-phase hiring approach with coding examples that often screens out potential candidates.
- Process: I enjoy improving process... especially if I can combine it with technology.
 I transitioned our sprints from spreadsheet to Trello.com boards and have gotten multiple teams to start using Trello as a process tracking mechanism (Dev, support, marketing, finance).
- **Company Direction**: As a member of the core team of managers at our company meet for regular stand-up meetings, monthly planning meetings, and annual planning meetings. I solely represent development/IT for the company.

Avidian Technologies Bellevue, WA 4/2008 - 6/2012

Principle Software Engineer

For this position, I was asked to help bring some engineering discipline to the team as well as help architect a transition from the traditional desktop app with a SQL backend to a hybrid SaaS based approach. This involved designing a centralized data center with distributed databases. Further, object-oriented-design practices were not in place and the code contained many redundancies that were very difficult to navigate and maintain. Below are some of the specific tasks I embarked on with regards to quality of the product and refactoring of the architecture:

- **Assembly Decomposition**: Started from 3 assemblies, I decomposed the code into layers in order to separate out the UI from the business and data layers.
- General Application Stability: Resolved hundreds of warnings, re-enabled strict data typing (in vb.net code), shored up error handling and logging, and fixed many crashing unhandled exceptions.
- Introduced Multi-Tier Architecture: Re-architecture of the application into Client, Webservice, and Data layers. Formerly client code called directly into SQL.

- **Rescued Failing Mobile Application:** Rescued a failing outsourced mobile web project written in HTML5 and jQuery from a broken mess to a production application.
- **Designed/Implemented Mobile Web-services**: Created a new light weight web-service layer optimized for mobile devices.
- **Threading**: Introduced multi-threading into badly needed areas of the application that was formerly 100% single threaded.
- Designed and Implemented CRM Cloud Infrastructure: Created from scratch our new cloud platform which included a new central registration database, multiple data server and multiple webserver farm behind an LVS load balancer.

LexisNexis Applied Discovery Bellevue, WA 2/2005 - 4/2008

Senior-Lead Software Development Engineer

Applied Discovery (ADI) handles the electronic evidence discovery of documents. We serviced some of the largest law firms in the country and were widely known as a premier service provider of electronic discovery. ADI handles a large variety of file types and processes them into actionable evidence by extracting meta-data and attachments and converting the native files into a Acrobat PDF file for review in our hosted Online Review Application (ORA).

In this position, I quickly came up to speed in and was assigned an email expander (processing of Outlook and Lotus Notes files... extraction of meta-data and attachments, and generation of PDF representations of emails). Was promoted to Lead to head of all email expansion (team of 4) within 8 months due to my work on our Lotus Notes expander. In the Q1 of 2006 my team and I gained responsibility of the development of all production tools used in the processing of the native data for release on the ORA.

Later I was heavily involved in the adoption of the agile SCRUM software development methodology and headed up the first SCRUM project in our department with positive results.

Technologies/Languages: vb.net, c#, MS SQL 2000-2005, grid based blade processing architecture.

LexisNexis Applied Discovery Bellevue, WA 2/2004 - 2/2005

Quality Assurance Lead

Lead a brand new team tasked with taking testing a suite of tools that had little to no documentation and began the process of testing new versions of the tools. The tools were part of a production system in which client documents in numerous file formats are converted in to Adobe PDF files. Each tool interfaced directly to the client database selected. As QA lead, I was responsible for understanding the technical workings of the system, assigning out new projects to my team (of 3), and supporting the team in their tasks. I also performed a good deal of testing in the following areas: SQL db and schema, data culling ("Staging") tool, Lotus Notes conversion, Zip expansion tool, Outlook PST expansion.

Technologies Used

- MS SQL Server 2000, TSQL, Profiler
- MS Visual Studio and C# Winforms
- Mercury Test Directory (administrator for production QA): custom scripted defect workflow.

SAS Institute Inc.

Beaverton, OR 2001 - 2003

Software Development Engineer

A member of the SAS Activity Based Management (ABM) development team. The software models a business's resources, activities, and deliverables and calculates the true cost of those deliverables. This data is then used to generate OLAP cubes using Microsoft Analysis Services (MSAS) and Crystal reports. This allows a business to rethink their business plan and streamline their processes.

Technically, ABM consists of an MFC rich client, business tier, web server, MSAS, and MS SQL database. The architecture is based on Microsoft's distributed architecture (aka N-Tier or DNA). While I worked in several areas, my specialty was in the UI of the rich client. The rich client uses the document-view design where each view consists of an MS IE browser control. Most dialogs are MFC based and most wizards are DHTML (JavaScript) based in the IE DOM. Below are some brief descriptions of my assignments.

- Developed complex MFC wizards and dialogs. Some included use of grid controls such as Stringray and MFCGrid.
- Responsible for developing the use of a ProClarity OLAP cube viewer tool
- This involves connecting the MFC and HTML UI elements to the proper ProClarity objects and methods. This was one of the three main views of the product.
- Developed hybrid DHTML wizards with ActiveX controls to create a richer UI experience
- Leveraged SOAP and XML web services.
- Owner of the Internationalization (I18N) Design of ABM. Also responsible for modifying all use of strings across C++, VB, JavaScript, and C# languages to utilize a coherent set of string resources.
- Owner/designer of QA test harness from SilkTest into the client for automating ActiveX controls. The call stack was SilkTest to C dll to MFC Client to COM.

ABC Technologies Inc. Beaverton, OR

From: 2000 To: 2001

Software Quality Assurance Engineer/Lead

Promoted because of my technical competence with the Oros product suite, test automation using Rational Visual Test 6.0, and my accomplishments in the former position. Became an expert with Visual Test and was the primary programmer in the group. I enjoyed helping others take it to new levels. Excelled at writing useful functions into the common library (include files), some leveraging the Win32API. Specific tasks included:

- Created test plans and test specifications
- Found a replacement for our defect tracking system.
- Responsible for QA development on the primary product in the suite, ABC Modeler.
- Extensive work on automation scripting due to significant changes and the poor shape of the existing scripts.
- QA lead of the Oros product suite for the release of Oros 5.2...Planning and Budgeting.

ABC Technologies Inc. Beaverton, OR

From: 1999 To: 2000

Software Quality Assurance Engineer

Early responsibilities included installation and system integration testing for the Oros suite of products in a client-server architecture. This involved system configuration including hardware and OS installation. My responsibilities then grew to include ownership of the test lab, the defect tracking system, and writing MS Visual test scripts. Specific tasks included:

- Solely responsible for all installation and configuration testing. This involved many configurations of our product suite and several server client configurations.
- Completed two Microsoft Certified Systems Engineer (MCSE) classes. Became a Microsoft Certified Professional on NT workstation.
- Solely implemented an independent NT Domain for the test lab (~10 machines) with trusts to the corporate NT Domain. Continued as test lab domain admin.

- Wrote Test Specifications, reviewed Functional Specifications.
- Given sole responsibility for the Visual Intercept defect tracking system administration.
- Began writing Microsoft Visual Test automated test scripts. Later was assigned the maintenance of all regression testing of our main product ABC Modeler.
- Wrote a script that was kicked off by an email Inbox rule that would install the product, reboot my machine, and run the nightly smoke regression suite. This allowed me to analyze the results of the nightly build the following morning and advise the rest of the QA team.

Boeing Commercial Airplanes Everett, WA From: 1997

To: 1999

Hydraulic Systems Engineer

- Worked in the Commercial Airplane Hydraulic Systems Analysis and Certification group.
- Created hydraulic component and/or system tests plan and test specifications for ground or flight-testing.
- Responsible for analysis and certification work on the 767, 747, and 777. Followed FAA code while implementing hydraulic system procedures, test plans, and designs.
- Rewarded for leadership and initiative in a successful 747 Rolls Royce Engine Certification included flight test procedures, test support, and analysis.

Education

Oregon Graduate Institute (OGI): OGI 515: Data Structures and Discrete Mathematics, CSE500 Introduction to Software Engineering

University of Washington | Seattle, WA Bachelor of Science, Mechanical Engineering